<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to another letter from Legorn, to an eminent merchant in Lond. Octob. 29. 1680</title>
            <author>P. J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11530</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13301431</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13301431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98924</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98924)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 459:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to another letter from Legorn, to an eminent merchant in Lond. Octob. 29. 1680</title>
                  <author>P. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: P. J.</note>
                  <note>Referring to the alleged popish plot.  Cf. B.M.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>From aboard the Van-herring: another letter from Legorn.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98924:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98924:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO ANOTHER Letter from Legorn, To an Eminent Merchant in <hi>Lond. Octob.</hi> 29. 1680.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received yours from Aboard the <hi>Van-herring,</hi> and doubtleſs there is no queſtion to be made but the <hi>Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Algerines</hi> are as buſie, not only of our great Ship the <hi>Van-herring,</hi> but of the <hi>Lyon Rampant,</hi> and the <hi>Golden Harp</hi> that attend her. You make me tremble to hear of the Contrivance which was among the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> to have blown up the Captain and his Council of Officers in the place it ſelf, at what time both He and they ſhould have been met together. We are not alſo ignorant how they would have Attack'd our ſingle Veſſel with a great <hi>Armado,</hi> having no other intention but to deſtroy and ſink her.</p>
            <p>Theſe were their Villanous attempts ſome years ago. But to come cloſer to the point, as you well obſerve, it was but the other day, that they put fire to the great Cabin, and burnt it level with the water. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it brought ſuch a Conſternation upon the hon<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Mariners, that had in all probability done their work, had they been as nimble to ſecond, as they were to act.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98924:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
As to the reſt of their Malicious deſigns, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of the diſcontented Mariners that were ſecur'd in the Gun-Room, and favour'd by the Lieutenant, I ſhall make no repetition thereof, but tell you how far we may rationally hope for an Alteration of affairs in our Ship. In the firſt place, The Perſon who is chiefly entruſted with the great Cabin, and the two Boatſwains, are ſuch now newly Choſen, for which the Mariners have a high reſpect, as being confident of their great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for the good of the Ship. There is one among them that has a great ſhare in looking after the great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, for whom the Mariners have not ſo great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as believing him too much a favourer of the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant's deſigns. Him therefore they are about to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, and 'tis thought 'twill be ſpeedily done; For that upon miſ-apprehenſions between the Mariners and the Lieutenant, he would be always giving Sentence to the prejudice of the Mariners, by which they thought their Rights and Priviledges impair'd.</p>
            <p>The Grand Council of the Officers of the Ship are now Sitting, and are very intent to diſcover the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigners and Deſigns that have been, and ſtill are, againſt the Ship. Before they Sate, the Lieutenant remov'd into the <hi>Lyon Rampant,</hi> at which the Impeach'd Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that are ſecur'd in the Gun-Room, were not a little penſive, and hung down their heads; as indeed they have reaſon enough to do. For though one of the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that accus'd them to the Captain, be ſince dead, yet there is another come in, that has Diſcover'd much more. His Teſtimony was ſomewhat decry'd at firſt by ſome of the Lieutenant's Friends; but now, 'tis believ'd more favour will be ſhown him, and that Credit be given to his Oath, that a perſon ſo much a Creature of the <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> may deſerve. That which did him no ſmall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98924:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
kindneſs, was this, That the very firſt day that the Grand Council of Officers ſate, he diſcover'd a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Mahometan,</hi> who was walking in diſguiſe upon the Deck among the great Officers in the Ship, and hearkening to their diſcourſes. But the great Officers order'd him to be laid hold on; inſomuch that the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant's friend was forc'd to commit him into the Hole, upon the Teſtimony of that Mariner, which he had ſo much ſlighted before: He has repeated his Diſcoveries before the Grand Council of Officers, who have heard him with great attention, and ſeem to be not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at what he has ſaid, and have order'd him to give in what he ſpoke by word of mouth, in Writing. One of the Members of the Great Council it ſelf, is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſuſpended, till he clear himſelf of ſome things which are laid to his Charge. There have been ſeveral Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, who have endeavoured by Papers and Writings to ſet the Captain and his Great Council at Varience. 'Tis thought the Eye of the Great Council will be ſoon upon them, in regard that they have already ſent for one of them, who, 'tis thought, truſted too much to the quickneſs of his Parts, and play'd too much upon the Diſcovery of the great Plot againſt the Captain and the Ship. Thereupon the ſaid Mariner, lately made a Quarter-Maſter, has left the Ship, or at leaſt ſo hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf among the Ballaſt and Cordage, that he cannot at preſent be found. Some of the Mariners inform againſt him, that he is a <hi>Mahometan,</hi> and has been ſo for many years. As for the Ships Cock-boat, which the <hi>Algerines,</hi> the moſt perfidious people in the world, do ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to cut from her Stern, we are in great hopes that particular care will be taken of it, in regard the Captain himſelf recommended the preſervation thereof to the Grand Council of Officers. Particular care will be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98924:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
alſo taken, no doubt, of the Golden Harp, where a ſtrict enquiry will be made after the <hi>Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Algerines,</hi> that have rais'd Mutinies and Diviſions among the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners on that Veſſel, on purpoſe to betray that Ship to the <hi>Argerines</hi> themſelves. In theſe and all thoſe other concerns which you mention, we make no queſtion but that the Grand Council of Officers will be very ſedulous for the good of the Ship. There is that Harmony at preſent between the Captain and them, which makes all the Mariners throw up their Caps, and rejoyce at no rate; Nay the very Mariners are turn'd devout too, and pray for the Continuance of it with the greateſt Zeal in the world: As being abſolutely confirm'd in this Opinion, That if that bleſſing befall them, that neither they nor their Ship will ever fall into the power of their Enemies, either the <hi>Mahometans</hi> or the <hi>Algerines,</hi> whom they will have no reaſon to fear, if their Captain and the Grand Council agree. By the next expect a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Account from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>P. J.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-head Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter: Row.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
